Titi me preguntó si hay muchos genocidios, hey, muchos genocidios, hoy Palestina, Congo, Sudán, hey, mañana hay otra.
Well, para mi gente, I'm libre, aborico, en Gaza, and today we're going to talk about the Halftime Show.
I'm going to say some things you might not like, but guess what, I'm not going to lie to you.
I've been in ongoing genocide for almost two years.
There are genocides happening in Gaza, Palestine, Congo, and Sudan.
Now, is Bad Bunny Show anti-colonial?
No, not really.
Lady Gaga is a Zionist.
It platformed Zionists.
It didn't talk about the ongoing genocide in Palestine.
And it also was on the platform of an organization that supports homeland security and ICE agents that are terrorizing our communities.
Now, it doesn't mean that there wasn't good symbolism, right?
Seeing flags and seeing the sugarcane fields.
My grandpa was a heat bottle.
He used to cut sugarcane.
Like, I get it.
But we had to move past symbolism.
Presentation alone is not revolutionary.
We should know this by now.
We have to note that this representation that we're seeing is just to calm us down.
The extrajudicial killings that have been happening.
ICE agents have at least extrajudicially massacred nine people.
Our Haitian brother died in the detention center.
The US military has extrajudicially killed 124 people in the Caribbean region and continues to attack the sovereignty of Caribbean and Latin American nations.
While using a halftime show to distract people and to paint this idea of multiculturalism and that the US is a place where everyone can mix and be kumbayash.
And that's just not true.
It doesn't lead to liberation.
Ricardo wrote about this in a post that you want to check out.
Ahora mismo, right now, the US attacking sovereignty everywhere.
There's three US warships outside of Haiti.
They just sent mercenaries to Haiti.
The US is backing a fascist dictator in la República Dominicana.
The US continues to impose a genocidal blockade on Cuba, who only has a few days left of fuel, has military installations in Trinidad and Tobago.
The US is kidnapping the president of Venezuela, threatening Nicaragua and Cuba and Colombia and any country that doesn't want to do what it says.
And Borinquen, the country that Bad Bunny comes from, is used as an imperialist launch pad for all these US foreign military interventions.
Not to mention that since 1898, the US has illegally occupied our country.
But hey, Bad Bunny's performing at the Super Bowl.
The Super Bowl show was in Spanish and, you know, they used the light blue flag.
Those things are great.
You also have to recognize that they're purely symbolic.
It's not stopping the ice raids.
Bad Bunny did not use this platform to amplify the ongoing genocide happening here in Palestina.
And I'm not saying he's perfect, but everybody at this point knows very well what's happening.
On top of that, he was wearing Zara with a Zionist company that we are currently boycotting.
And it makes us feel good.
Feel good for what?
We haven't stopped the genocides happening.
Gazans are surviving a genocide.
And we don't get no mood boosters because we don't have time for that.
So they're using Bad Bunny to pacify Latino and Caribbean people and people of color.
And they've done this with black culture too.
You know, think about after the George Floyd uprisings.
How many halftime performances and uplifting of black culture were happening to distract people from the fatal executions that continue.
They're using black excellence to distract people.
This is not a new thing.
They're weaponizing culture to keep you pacified, to calm you down, right?
Because now there's Bad Bunny.
And you're going to talk less about ICE.
And you're not going to talk about, you know, these Epstein followers.
Don't get me wrong.
Yo soy boricua, pa' que tu lo sepa.
Like, I'm proud.
I'm proud of this.
But at the same time, I understand that it's a symbol.
And symbols aren't going to get us the tangible things that we need for the liberation of Borinquen,
for the end of foreign military intervention in IT.
To get the U.S. out of Latin America and the Caribbean so that we can be sovereign nations, unified against imperialism.
Symbols aren't going to end the genocide in Palestine, in the Congo, in Sudan.
So we got to be more serious.
You know, like, it's not that serious.
Yes, it is.
Coño.
We're being bombed.
We're being killed.
After this, there's going to be no organizing.
And that's the problem.
It's simply representation.
Most people, this isn't going to move them to actually start organizing with an organization for the tangible changes that we need.
Puerto Rican's have American citizenship.
I'm sorry.
You can miss me with that one.
I don't know any country in their right mind that would give up their sovereignty, independence, dignity, and self-respect for a passport from the colonizer in exchange for their homeland.
That doesn't even make sense.
Oh, there's a privilege.
Privilege to be colonized?
And I'll recommend that you all read The War Against All Puerto Ricans by Nelson Dennis and Puerto Rico and National History by Yorel Melendez Vadillo to get a better understanding and to get a historical understanding of what it means to be boricua, what it means to be colonized and repressed by the U.S. for fighting for our rights, for resisting our colonization.
It's even more important that we understand that culture in and of itself is not going to liberate us, right?
We need a culture of revolution that moves us towards tangible actions instead of falling for these colonial tricks to pacify us using our own culture.
You know, Bad Bunny talks about los apagones, you know, the blackouts.
He talks about our forced displacement, that, you know, we don't want to become like Hawaii.
And he sings about the real everyday struggles of our people.
At the end of the day, it unifies us in emotions and feelings.
We need to convert those feelings, those emotions that aren't into actions.
We move past the symbolism and towards the tangible material changing of our lives conditions.